# Curriculum Vitae

PD Dr. phil. Stefan Groth https://www.stefangroth.com

Version: 1d0789a, 2021-11-22

### Work Address

University Duisburg-Essen Schifferstraße 44 DE-47059 Duisburg

Phone: +49 203 379 5267 Email: stefangroth@me.com

# **Current Position**

since 03/2021	Privatdozent, Institute of Social Anthropology and Cultural Studies (ISEK) – Popular Cul-
	ture Studies, University of Zurich.
since 11/2021	Senior Research Fellow, Centre for Global Cooperation Research, University Duisburg-
	Essen.
04/2022-	Upcoming: Visiting Professor (spring term 2022), Ludwig-Uhland-Institute for Empirical Cul-
09/2022	tural Studies, University Tübingen.

# **Research Interests**

Political Anthropology and Europeanization Studies; Narratology, Linguistic Anthropology and Ethnography of Communication; Cultural Heritage and Cultural Property; Methods in Empirical Cultural Studies; Sport as Cultural Practice; Ethnography of Organizations.

# **Research Projects**

2021-2023	Everyday Narratives of (De-)Legitimation: How Stories about Migration Policies and Expert
	Regimes are told in Everyday Contexts (Senior Fellowship Centre for Global Cooperation
	Research).
since 2021	The Everyday: Perspectives from Empirical Cultural Studies (Book Project).
since 2021	Europe from Outside and from the Margins: The Everyday Production of Europe in Bor-
	derlands and Non-European Contexts.
since 2019	Popular Narratives of the Political.
2016-2020	The Middle as Practice and Constellation: Orientations towards the Middle from the Per-
	spective of Empirical Cultural Studies (Habilitation).
since 2013	Dimensions of Popular Sports: Cycling and Running as Sport and Leisure from the Perspec-
	tive of Empirical Cultural Studies.

Ι

since 2014	Qualitative Approaches to International Institutions (with Katja Freistein, Alejandro Es-
2014-2015	guerra). Culture as Resource and Diplomacy: Between Geopolitics and Issues-Based Policy (Post-Doc Fellowship Käte Hamburger Kolleg/Centre for Global Cooperation Research).
2011-2014	The Ethics of / in Negotiating and Regulating Cultural Property (PI: Prof. Dr. Regina F. Bendix, DFG-Research Unit Cultural Property).
2008-2011	Communication Patterns and Decision-Making about Cultural Property in the International Forum of the World Intellectual Property Organization (PhD Project, PI: Prof. Dr. Regina F. Bendix, DFG-Research Unit Cultural Property).
	Positions Held
2016-2021	Head Laboratory Popular Culture Studies/Senior Research and Teaching Fellow, Popular Culture Studies, Institute of Social Anthropology and Cultural Studies (ISEK), University of Zurich.
2015-2016	Post-Doc, Cultural Anthropology/Folklore Studies, Institute of Archeology and Cultural Anthropology, University of Bonn.
2014-2015	Post-Doctoral Fellow, Käte Hamburger Kolleg/Centre for Global Cooperation Research, University Duisburg-Essen Project: Culture as Resource and Diplomacy: Between Geopolitics and Issues-Based Policy.
2011-2014	Post-Doc, Institute of Cultural Anthropology/European Ethnology, Georg-August-University Göttingen. Project: The Ethics of/in Negotiating and Regulating Cultural Property (Sub-Project, Interdisciplinary DFG Research Unit "The Constituting of Cultural Property: Actors, Discourses, Contexts, Rules").
2008-2011	Research Associate/Ph.D. Candidate, Institute of Cultural Anthropology/European Ethnology, Georg-August-University Göttingen. Project: Communication Patterns and Decision-Making about Cultural Property in the International Forum of the World Intellectual Property Organization (Sub-Project, "The Constituting of Cultural Property: Actors, Discourses, Contexts, Rules").
	Education
03/2021	Venia Legendi Empirical Cultural Studies (Privatdozent), University of Zurich (CH). Habilitation: "The Middle as Practice and Constellation: Orientations towards the Middle from the Perspective of Empirical Cultural Studies (submitted 11/2019)".
2008-2011	Dr. phil. in Cultural Anthropology/European Ethnology, Georg-August-University Göttingen (DE). PhD thesis: "Negotiating Tradition: The Pragmatics of International Deliberations on Cultural Property" ( <i>summa cum laude</i> ). Advisor: Prof. Dr. Regina F. Bendix (Göttingen), Prof. Dr. Donald F. Brenneis (UC Santa Cruz).
10/03-03/08	M.A. in Sociology, Subjects: Sociology, Cultural Anthropology/European Ethnology, Social and Economic Psychology, Georg-August-University Göttingen (DE). MA thesis: "Open-Source-Software Engineering: Sociological Discussion of a Specific Form of Innovation Networks (Entwicklung von Open-Source-Software: Soziologische Diskussion einer spezifischen Form von Innovationsnetzwerk)" (Sehr gut).
10/06-01/07	Erasmus Student Exchange Programme, Subjects: Relazioni Pubbliche (Public Relations),

Stays Abroad

Università degli Studi di Udine (IT).

03/10-04/10

DAAD (German Academic Exchange Service) Fellowship for Ph.D. Research Studies, Research Visits at University of Chicago, University of California at Santa Cruz, School for Advanced Research in Santa Fe, USA.

2012 Erasmus Teaching Staff Mobility Grant, Seminar für Kulturwissenschaft und Europäische

Ethnologie, University of Basel, Switzerland.

10/06-01/07 Erasmus Student Exchange Programme, Public Relations, Università degli Studi di Udine,

Italy.

## **Further Training and Qualifications**

02/2018 Presentation Skills, University of Zurich.

05/2017 Leadership Skills for Postdocs, University of Zurich.

o1/2017 Project Management for Successful Postdocs, University of Zurich.

10/2013 Gender-sensitive Didactics, Göttingen University.

2013–2014 Certificate Programme University Didactics, Göttingen University. Kurse:

Exams and Legal Aspects of Exams (01/2013); Activating Methods (03/2013); Basic Competences University Didactics I (03/2013); Presentation Skills and Rhetorics (05/2013); Cooperation in Teaching (06/2013); Basic Competences University Didactics I (07/2013); E-Learning-Tools (11/2013); Practice Talks (11/2013); Advising Students (01/2014).

#### Work in committees

2016–2021 Membership in Various University-, Faculty-, and Institute-Wide Working Groups at the

University of Zurich (Working Group Social Sciences, Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences, Zurich (2016–2021)/Development of Degree Courses, Working Group Qualitative Me-

thods at the UZH)

2018–2021 Board Member, Research Network Cultural Citizenship (University of Zurich, Zurich Uni-

versity of the Arts, Zurich University of Applied Science)

2017–2021 Co-Speaker, Section Cultures of Work, German Society of Folklore (dgv)

2017-2020 Delegate, Commission for Research and Promotion of Junior Researchers, Faculty of Arts

and Social Sciences, Zurich

2013-2019 H-Folk-Netzwerk, Editor

2015–2016 Board Member, Institute for Archeology and Cultural Anthropology, University of Bonn

Board Member, Center for Theory of Culture and Society, University of Göttingen, Germa-

ny

2010-2014

2014-2018

# Memberships

German Society for Empirical Cultural Studies (DGV)

Swiss Association for European Ethnology (SGV), Section Zurich

European Association of Social Anthropologists (EASA), EASA Networks Anthropology

of Law, Rights and Governance (LAWNET); Linguistic Anthropology (ELAN)

Societé Internationale d'Ethnologie et de Folklore (SIEF), SIEF Working Groups Narrative

Cultures; Cultural Heritage and Property

Rheinische Vereinigung für Volkskunde (RVV)

since 2021 DFG-Network on Experientiality

DFG-Network on Competition

Version 1d0789a, 2021-11-22, https://github.com/sgroth/cv-data

### **Teaching Activities**

A full list of taught courses is available at: https://github.com/sgroth/teaching

Empirical Cultural Studies, University of Tübingen, Germany
Cultural Studies/Anthropology, University of Zurich, Switzerland
Cultural Studies/European Ethnology, University of Bonn, Germany
Erasmus Teaching Staff Mobility Grant, Cultural Heritage, University of Basel, Switzerland
Cultural Anthropology/European Ethnology, University of Göttingen, Germany

#### Reviewer for

Reviewer for Journals: International Journal of Heritage Studies (IJHS), Anthropological Journal of European Cultures (AJEC), Narrative Culture, Zeitschrift für Volkskunde, Jahrbuch für Europäische Ethnologie, Global Cooperation Research Papers

### **BA** Theses

MA Theses: 2 Master Students (1 co-advised); Faculty of Arts and Social Sciences, Institute of Social Anthropology and Cultural Studies, University of Zurich, Switzerland; 1 Master Student (co-advised); Faculty of Arts, Department for Cultural Anthropology, University of Bonn, Germany; 1 Master Student; Faculty of Humanities, Institute of Cultural Anthropology/European Ethnology, Göttingen University, Germany

#### Organizational Activities

Head Laboratory Popular Culture Studies, Institute of Social Anthropology and Cultural Studies (ISEK), Zurich University (Conception and Execution, Senior Fellow-Program, Promotion of Young Scholars, Organisation of Conferences and In House-Workshops, Lectures, Panel Debates).

Organisation of Panels at Conferences (Deutsche Gesellschaft für Volkskunde, Société Internationale d'Ethnologie et de Folklore).

Upcoming: With Anna Weichselbraun, Ph.D.: Panel Talk and Temporality, dgv-Congress 2021, Regensburg, September 2021.

With Dr. Sarah May and Dr. Johannes Müske: Morality as Organizational Practice. 19th Workshop of the Section Cultures of Work of the German Association of Cultural Anthropology and Folklore Studies (dgv), Freiburg, November 2021.

With Dr. Sarah May, Work Meeting dgy-Section Cultures of Work, November 2020.

With Dr. Christine Hämmerling and Prof. Dr. Silke Meyer: Workshop Moral Economy, May 2019, Laboratory Popular Culture Studies, Zurich University.

With Prof. Dr. Markus Tauschek: Panel Comparison as Reflective and Affective Practice: Orientations Towards the Middle and Everyday Comparisons, SIEF-Kongress 2019, Santiago de Compostela, Spanien, 14-17. April 2019.

Panel Debate Everyday Knowledge. Places, Media, and Practices. Perspectives from Anthropology. Science Festivals 100 Ways of Thinking, Kunsthalle Zurich, Oktober 2018.

Organisation with Dr. Sarah May and Dr. Johannes Müske, Networked, Unbounded, Pre-

carious? Work in Social Discourse. 19th Workshop of the Section Cultures of Work of the German Association of Cultural Anthropology and Folklore Studies (dgv), September 2018. Zurich.

In-House-Workshop Research Support, with Prof. em. Dr. Silke Göttsch-Elten, May 2018, Laboratory Popular Culture Studies, Zurich University.

In-House-Workshop Rurality / Urbanity as Spatial Orders and Categories, May 2018, Laboratory Popular Culture Studies, Zurich University.

In-House-Workshop Researching Historically. April 2018, Labor Populäre Kulturen, ISEK, Universität Zürich.

Organisation with Dr. Christian Ritter (Collegium Helveticum, Zürich), Workshop Working Together. Practices of Coordination, Cooperation, and Representation in Collaborative Processes, October 2017, Laboratory Popular Culture Studies, Zurich University.

In-House-Workshop Perspectives of Ethnographic Cultural Analysis May 2017, Labor Populäre Kulturen, ISEK, Universität Zürich.

Organisation with Dr. Alejandro Esguerra (Potsdam) and Dr. Katja Freistein (Duisburg), International Workshop Micro-Moves in International Institutions, Standing Group Sociology of International Relations (AK SiB), February 9-10, 2017, Universität Potsdam.

Organisation with Dr. Katja Freistein (Duisburg) and Dr. Alejandro Esguerra Portocarrero (Duisburg), Interdisciplinary Workshop Studying Micro-Practices in (International) Institutions: Chances and Limitations of Theory-Building, November 26-27, 2015, Centre for Global Cooperation Research (GCR), Duisburg.

Organisation with Yonca Krahn (Zürich): Panel Sport und Sinne, dgv-Kongress 2015, Zürich, July 2015.

Organisation with Charles Briggs (UC Berkeley) and Regina Bendix, International Working Conference Justice in Discourse, April 4–5, 2013, Göttingen.

Organisation with Nadine Wagener-Böck M.A., Workshop "Subjektbegriffe der Europäischen Ethnologie" ("Concepts of the 'Subject' in European Ethnology"), December 13-14, 2012, Göttingen.

### **Expositions**

Places of Knowledge. Ethnographic/Artistic Explorations (05/2018, Zurich University of the Arts).